<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief apology in behalf of the people in derision call'd Quakers. Written for the information of our sober and well-inclined neighbors in and about the town of Warminster in the county of Wilts. by Will. Chandler, Alex. Pyott, Jo. Hodges, and some others.</title>
            <author>Chandler, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789215</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789215</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78566)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2637:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief apology in behalf of the people in derision call'd Quakers. Written for the information of our sober and well-inclined neighbors in and about the town of Warminster in the county of Wilts. by Will. Chandler, Alex. Pyott, Jo. Hodges, and some others.</title>
                  <author>Chandler, William.</author>
                  <author>Pyott, Alex. (Alexander)</author>
                  <author>Hodges, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Northcott ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references in margins.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172527:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief APOLOGY IN Behalf of the PEOPLE In Deriſion Call'd <hi>QUAKERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WRITTEN For the Information of our Sober and Well-inclined Neighbours in and about the Town of <hi>Warminſter</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>Will. Chandler, Alex. Pyot, I. Hodges,</hi> And ſome others.</p>
            <q>By honour and diſhonour, by evil report and good report, as deceivers and yet true, as unknown and yet well known, as dying and behold we live,</q>
            <bibl>2 Cor. 6. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Northcott</hi> in <hi>George-yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172527:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172527:2"/>
            <head>A Brief Apology, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is not that we love Contention, or deſire Controverſie, or are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient in bearing Reproaches, that we appear thus publick, but ſuch have been the repeated high Charges, and ſmart Laſhes that our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries (more eſpecially ſome of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Aſſembly) have of late ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a liberty, liberally and laviſhly to beſtow upon us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we find ourſelves concern'd to Clear and Vindicate the Truth and Innocency of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, from thoſe black aſperſions that have rendred it ſo frightful and formidable, as though 'twere only a meer complication of peſtilent Errors, as well as to ſatisfie the minds of ſuch of our piouſly-inclined Neighbours, as may be deſirous to hear us ſpeak for ourſelves, as alſo for the information of thoſe who may have been impoſed upon, by that dreſs wherein our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers have repreſented us. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172527:3"/>
theſe can Object nothing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial againſt us now that hath not been long ſince over and over offer'd by ſome of the ſame Perſwaſion, and have as often received Anſwers from ſome or other of our Friends, (ſome of which have never yet been by them replyed unto) yet foraſmuch as thoſe may not have come to the view of many of our Neighbours, for whom this is chiefly intended, we thought fit briefly to ſay ſo much as we think may be accommodate to the preſent occaſion; and which perhaps with unprejudic'd minds may beſpeak our Creed not ſo unſound and errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note place="margin">Eſth. 3. 5.</note> as our ſomewhat different deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath rendred us obnoxious and contemptible, as well as diſtaſteful to thoſe who either ambitiouſly affect ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour<note place="margin">Joh. 5. 44 Mat. 23.</note> and reſpect, and love greetings, or think a complaiſant complyance to the faſhions, cuſtoms, and complements of the Age, to be one of the chiefeſt felicities of this Life, and beſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Civility and good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>We therefore deſire our well-diſpoſed Neighbours, candidly to weigh what we have to alledge againſt the Clamours of thoſe, who to be ſure will not ſet us out to our beſt advantage, and to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172527:3"/>
receive an Account from ourſelves what we are, and what we believe and hold for Chriſtian Truths, who certainly muſt needs know better our own Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief than thoſe who perhaps never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd it, to any other end than to find fault, if ever they did it; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that you will not think it ſtrange, that we expreſs not our Belief in ſome particulars, in the affected Terms of other Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, but think it more reaſonable and ſafe to content ourſelves with that Dreſs of Language, in which the Holy Ghoſt thought fit to hand them to us in the Holy Scriptures; thoſe moſt Excellent and Divine Writings, which above all others in the world, challenge our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and moſt diligent reading, thoſe Oracles of God, &amp; rich Chriſtian Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of Divine ſaving Truths, which were written for our learning, that we<note place="margin">Ro. 15. 4.</note> through patience and comfort of them may have hope, and are profitable for doctrine, reproof, correction, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction<note place="margin">2 Tim. c. 3. v. 15, 16, 17.</note> in righteouſneſs, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting and thoroughly furniſhing of the Man of GOD to every good Work, making him wiſe unto ſalvation thro' Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all Chriſtian Doctrines neceſſary
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172527:4"/>
to be believed for ſalvation, and are a ſufficient external ſtandard and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to try the Doctrines of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and we ſay with the Apoſtle, whoſoever ſhall<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8.</note> publiſh, and propagate any other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and Faith than is therein teſtified of to us, by thoſe inſpired Pen-men who were the firſt Promulgators thereof, though he were an Angel let him be accurſed; all which, and whatſoever is therein contained, we as firmly believe as any of you do; and as 'tis the duty of every ſincere Chriſtian, we are hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily thankful to God for them, who through his good Providence hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved them to our Time, to our great benefit and comfort.</p>
            <p>We Believe in that Great Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent God, that made and created all things, and gave us our Being, whom in ſincerity of heart we fear, reverence and worſhip, being ſeriouſly concern'd for our ſouls welfare to eternity. We believe that Great Myſtery, that there are Three that bear Record in Heaven,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 7.</note> the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and that theſe Three are One in Being and Subſtance: And as do ye, ſo do we alſo hope for and expect Salvation, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and alone through the Son of God our bleſſed Lord and Saviour JESUS
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172527:4"/>
CHRIST of <hi>Nazareth;</hi> believing that God the Father hath ordained him for<note place="margin">Iſa. 49. 6. Act. 13. 47 &amp; 4. 12.</note> ſalvation to the ends of the Earth; and that no other Name is given under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by which men ſhall be ſaved; who being conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> was born of her at <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> as alſo his Holy<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 21, 22. Heb. 4. 15.</note> and Exemplary Life, perfectly free from ſin; his Doctrine, Miracles, Sufferings, and Death upon the Croſs, without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> his Reſurrection from the Dead, and Aſcenſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">Ro. 8. 34. 1 Tim. 2. 5, 6. 1 Jo. 2. 1. 2.</note> where he is at the Right Hand of God the Father, perfect GOD and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Man, and the alone Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween GOD and Man, and is our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate with the Father, and ever liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to make Interceſſion for us; and alſo ſhall judge both Quick and Dead:<note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 42</note> All which, and whatſoever elſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of him in the Sacred Scriptures, we firmly believe.</p>
            <p>This Jeſus, in whom dwelt the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<note place="margin">Col. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the God-head, we believe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd up himſelf according to the Will of the Father, an acceptable ſacrifice to<note place="margin">Eph. 52. 1 Joh. 2. 2. Heb. 10. 12</note> God, and became a Propitiation for the ſins of Mankind, <hi>to the end of the World,</hi> and dyed for all Men, as all dyed in<note place="margin">Rom. 5. v. 12. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Adam;</hi> through whoſe Blood God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172527:5"/>
Redemption and Salvation to<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 19.</note> Man, and offers to be reconciled, and freely for his Sons ſake to remit, forgive<note place="margin">Ro. 3. 25.</note> and paſs by all paſt offences to as many as ſhall truly and heartily repent of their<note place="margin">Luk. 24. 47. Acts 10. 43. &amp; 26. 20. Eph. 4. 22. 23. 24. Ro. 8. 3. 4. 2 Cor. 5. 15. 17. Tit. 2. 14. Joh. 14. 15. 21. 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24. &amp; 15. 10 2 Tim. 2. 19. 1 Pet. 4. 1, 2, 3. Jam. 2. 12. to the end.</note> ſins, and turn from the ſame, and ſhall ſo believe in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and love him as for the future to live a holy Circumſpect Chriſtian life, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his commands, thereby continuing in his love.</p>
            <p>Which holy life ſo much Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſtrictly kept to in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Ages of Chriſtianity, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever named the name, or took the name of Chriſt upon them were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity, we believe ought to be inſeparable from a true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtian as ever accompanying a true living and active Faith; and it ſeems was thought no leſs neceſſary by thoſe who compoſed the promiſe that ſhould be made in behalf of infants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were admitted into that once ſacred Catalogue, (to wit) that as they<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12.</note> came to years of diſcretion, they ſhould forſake the devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked world, and all the ſinful luſts of the<note place="margin">Luk. 1. 75</note> fleſh, and keep Gods holy will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and walk in the ſame all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172527:5"/>
the days of their lives: This we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve<note place="margin">Ro. 6. 18, 19, 22. 2 Cor. 7. 1. Eph. 4. 24 Theſ 3. 13 &amp; 4. 7. Heb. 12. 10. 14. 1 Joh. 4. 4.</note> to be the bounden duty of mankind, and though our Oppoſers have ſcoft us, and branded us with error for hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perfection, becauſe in pleading for a holy righteous life as that which is well-pleaſing to God, and avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his power to be ſtronger in man, as man cleaves to it, and believes to reſcue him from under the power of Satan, than is that of the devil to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>train him in Thraldom, we have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made uſe of the words of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as be you perfect as<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 48 Col. 4. 12. 1 Joh. 3. 3.</note> your Father which is in Heaven is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, he that hath this hope in him, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth himſelf even as he is pure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet have we never pretended to a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perfection beyond what is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the above promiſe, which is ſound and true in it ſelf, and is that which God requires of us; and therefore 'tis that we frequently preſs it's neceſſity, and fervently exhort people to its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. And notwithſtanding we have hence been falſely accuſed that we expect to be ſaved by our own works as being Meritorious, yet we don't ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a holy life as the Efficient and procuring Cauſe of our Salvation; which we no leſs than you totally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172527:6"/>
to the free Grace, and mercy of<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 8.</note> God in Chriſt without any merit in Man, but we eſteem it as a conſtant compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">James 2. 18. to the end.</note> thereto, and a neceſſary condition on our part in complyance with God's gracious offer, without which we may not obtain it, being inſeparably annext<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6. Ro. 12. 1. 2.</note> to that Faith which only pleaſeth God, and is but our reaſonable duty.</p>
            <p>And we believe that although Chriſt<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 9. &amp; 10. 12.</note> thus offer'd up himſelf once for all, for the ſins of all men to the end of the world, thereby rendring repentance and amendment of life prevalent with God; yet that the Traditional Belief of that alone is not ſufficient to entitle us to that common Salvation that comes by him, but that 'tis of neceſſity that we truly repent and be converted from<note place="margin">Act. 3. 19</note> the evil to the good, and therefore 'tis no leſs neceſſary for us now than 'twas for believers in the Apoſtles days, that<note place="margin">&amp; 26. 18. 20.</note> we be turned from darkneſs to light, or in otherterms, from the dark power of Satan, to the power of God who is light, that thereby we may every one know the work of Redemption and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, wrought in and for our ſelves: For 'tis not enough to believe that Chriſt dyed, if we feel not the bleſſed effects of his death, who came to ſave
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172527:6"/>
us from our ſins, and bleſs us by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Mat. 1. 21. Act. 3. 26. Tit. 2. 14.</note> us from our iniquities, and gave himſelf for us that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himſelf a peculiar people zealous of good works.</p>
            <p>For we believe ſuch to be the natural<note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17 Ro. 5. 12. 2 Cor. 5. 14. Gen. 6. 5. Ro. 7. 5.</note> State of Man in the fall, that by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we are dead as to God, at a diſtance from him prone to evil, and to gratify the deſires of our ſenſual<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> minds, ſway'd by the corrupt and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 2.</note> luſts of the fleſh, and under the power of a ſtrange King, rul'd by the<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 26.</note> Prince of the Power of the air, ſo that our inward man being thus dead from God, we cannot exerciſe our ſpiritual ſenſes towards him, nor can this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> man perceive, know, or ſavour the things of God, which only arc ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually diſcerned; wherefore, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our Saviour dyed for us, we are yet by nature in a miſerable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done condition, in Captivity to our ſouls Enemy, except we know the ſecond<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 45. 47. Eph. 2. 1. 5 Col. 2. 13. Ro. 8. 11. Eph. 5. 13. 14. Joh. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> the Lord from Heaven, that quickning ſpirit, to quicken our ſouls, and make us alive to God again, that being reſtored to the uſe of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſes, we may by the aſſiſtance of his Divine Light (wherewith for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172527:7"/>
that end he hath bleſt all the Sons and<note place="margin">Eph, 2. 3. &amp; 5. 6.</note> Daughters of Men) ſee our ſelves in this ſad and loſt ſtate under the wrath of God, and abhor our ſelves therefore, and under this living ſenſe (wherein things will appear with another aſpect than before) cry to God for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance therefrom, with ſuch and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 10.</note> hearty ſorrow as works a true repentance for the ſame. 'Tis not our being ſprinkled, when infants, that will make us true Chriſtians, convert us from<note place="margin">Joh. 1. 12. 13. Ro. 8. 14.</note> being children of wrath to become children of grace, and Sons of God, and members of Chriſts Church, and inveſt us in an intereſt in him; 'tis not learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Catechiſm and ſubſcribing to certain Articles of Faith, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo Orthodox, and being educated in a hiſtorical belief of what Chriſt did for us above ſixteen hundred years ago; 'tis not this only that will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter a ſufficient, true, and ſaving knowledge of Chriſt, and really inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt us in his death and ſufferings, all which people may talk of and pleaſe themſelves withal, and yet continue as faſt bound under the dominion of Satan (who ſtill rules where diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is) as thoſe leſs perfect in that leſſon, but the true and ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172527:7"/>
of Chriſt is to know our ſelves<note place="margin">Act. 26. 18</note> turn'd from darkneſs to light, from the power of Satan to the power of<note place="margin">Col. 1. 13.</note> God, that by it we may be delivered from the power of darkneſs, and be tranſlated into the Kingdom of his dear Son, to know his ſaving power really to reſcue and redeem us from<note place="margin">Joh. 8. 32. 36.</note> under the power of him that hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrald us, and leads Captive at his will<note place="margin">Mar. 3. 27</note> thoſe who lives in the vanity of their minds, to know him bind this ſtrong man, to ſpoil his goods and diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs,<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 2. 3</note> and caſt him out, to know Chriſt to ſit in the ſoul as a refiner, to burn<note place="margin">Luk. 3. 16, 17. Ro. 15. 16. Joh. 13. 8. 1 Theſ. 5. 23. 1 Cor. 1. 2 Joh. 14. 23 Heb. 13. 21</note> up, conſume and deſtroy, to purify and throughly to purge out whatſoever is contrary to him, to waſh us and make us clean that we may have rightto a part in him, that being cleanſed and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, he may take up his abode with us exerciſing his Kingly power, and working in us both to will and to do of his good pleaſure. The mind being thus diſentangled, and having caſt off its former yoke, the old things being done away, all things now become new;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17. Ezek. 36. 26.</note> a new tender heart of fleſh according to the promiſe, new thoughts, deſires, inclinations, affections, words, actions, this new inſide producing a new out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172527:8"/>
alſo, even throughout a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 26.</note> now in Chriſt indeed, and really entitled to thoſe benefits that accrue to men through him; that living faith that pleaſeth God and gives victory,<note place="margin">Jam. 2. 18, to the end. Heb. 12. 2</note> and is ever fruitful to him in good works, being begotten, and this work of Redempton and Regeneration thus wrought in the ſoul by Jeſus Chriſt, together with that moſt precious ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice he offer'd up, when his Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood Shed upon the Croſs for us, we believe compleats the ſalvation of every ſoul that is thus awakened, and made alive, and ſet free, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<note place="margin">Ro. 6. 11. 13. Joh. 8. 36</note> and ſpirit of him that is the way, the truth, and the life of every ſoul that truly lives to God, to walk in that holy way of life, truth, and peace, that was prepared of old for the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed<note place="margin">Iſa. 35. 8, 9.</note> and redeemed to walk in.</p>
            <p>And we believe that he graciouſly waits with exceeding great kindneſs, and long ſuffering, that men may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, knocking at the door of every<note place="margin">Rev. 3. 20</note> mans heart, freely offering, but not impoſing his aſſiſtance to this moſt<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 37.</note> concerning work and change in the minds of men; ſo that in the day wherein God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will judge the world by Jeſus Chriſt, and every ſecret thing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172527:8"/>
will be made manifeſt, God will be juſtified and clear of the Blood of all Men, and every mouth will be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and every Man's Condemnation will be of himſelf for having rejected the day of his viſitation, wherein God calls to Man, and offers to be reconciled to him for reſiſting the ſtrivings, and ſlighting the reproofs of his ſpirit,<note place="margin">Neh. 9. 20.</note> which in matchleſs mercy he hath giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en man to inſtruct him, and ſhew, and lead him in the way of life and peace.</p>
            <p>We believe, that though the pravity of mans nature in the fall, is ſuch, that the Natural or Carnal Man, that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt God in the ſtate of meer nature, minds only the things of the<note place="margin">Ro. 8. 5. 7. 8.</note> fleſh, and naturally brings forth the works thereof, and cannot pleaſe God, nor keep and obſerve his Laws, but is prone to evil; yet that thoſe who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the viſitation of God, and are<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 23.</note> really regenerated and born again of incorruptible ſeed, by the word of God<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> that lives and abides forever, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted<note place="margin">Jam. 1. 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> word that is quick and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and able to ſave and ſanctify the<note place="margin">Joh. 17. 17. 19.</note> ſoul, are born into a new life, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with another and higher power, and becomes ſpiritually minded, and by the ſpirit are ſet at liberty to walk af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 6.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:172527:9"/>
the ſpirit, and bring forth it's fruits, and receives ability from the ſpirit to ſerve God acceptably, being now led<note place="margin">Ro. 8. 14. 15.</note> by the ſpirit of God and become his Children, taught of him, and through the ſpirit of adoption receiv'd into their hearts, have right to call God Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 3. Ro. 8. 13. &amp; 6. 6. Eph. 4. 22 23. 24. Gal. 5. 24 Col. 3. 9. 10.</note> and Jeſus Lord, for having through the ſpirit mortified the Old Man or firſt Nature, with his corrupt and depraved inclinations and evil deeds, and put him off, having crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts thereof, they put on the New and Heavenly Man, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God is created in righteouſneſs and true holineſs, and being renewed in the ſpirit of their minds, they now walk in<note place="margin">Ro. 6. 4. &amp; 7. 6.</note> Newneſs of Life, and are really in Chriſt, and therefore are changed and become new Creatures, and now thinks and acts under the conduct of a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Superiour to that which formerly governed them, having their minds raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a Region above that of fallen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo that now the ſtream of their thoughts, deſires and actions, runs in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother current, and the bent of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are after thoſe things that are above where Chriſt is; that eye being<note place="margin">Col. 3. 1. 2.</note> now open'd that ſees a more tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent beauty and deſireableneſs in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172527:9"/>
and durable treaſures of him, than all the tranſcient felicities of this world can afford.</p>
            <p>And we believe that whoſoever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects the bleſſed imputation of Chriſt's<note place="margin">Ro. 13. 14.</note> righteouſneſs, ought thus to put on the Lord Jeſus, and to be thus cloathed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and covered with his righteouſneſs, and in meaſure have his Holy Life brought forth in and through them, and and know him to enliven and influence their minds, and to work in and for<note place="margin">Iſa. 26. i2. Phil. 2. i3. Phil. 4. 13. Joh. i5. 5.</note> them, and that without him they can do nothing, but thro' him that ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens them, they can do whatſoever he commands them, that as they abide liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing branches in him, through that ſap and vertue they dayly receive from him,<note place="margin">Joh. 15. 5, 8.</note> they are made able to bring forth fruits well-pleaſing to God, whereby he is glorified. For though God the Father accepts us in Chriſt, and for his ſake; yet is the New-Birth the indiſpenſible Qualification, and true diſtinguiſhing Mark of thoſe that are really in him. He<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17. Gal. 6. i5. 1 Joh. 2. 6. &amp; 30. 7. 8, 9.</note> that is in Chriſt is a new Creature, <hi>Old things are paſt away, behold all things are become New. John</hi> ſays, <hi>He that ſaith he abideth in him, ought himſelf alſo, ſo to walk even as he walked.</hi> We aſcribe nothing to Man, as having any power or ability in or of himſelf to pleaſe God,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172527:10"/>
but attribute all power to do that which<note place="margin">Joh. 15. 4, 5.</note> is good to Chriſt alone, in whom only the Father is well-pleaſed. 'Tis through him that men ſo love and fear God as to eſchew evil, and work that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<note place="margin">Acts 10. 34, 35.</note> which is acceptable to him; upon whom therefore mans dependance ought to be dayly, to receive from him ſuch ſuitable ſupplies, as through a conſtant watchfulneſs may enable them ſo to walk, as to continue in his favour and enjoy his ſmiles: For 'tis not as too many ſeem either to imagine, or would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have it to be, that they may live in ſin and diſobedience here, and indulge their corrupt inclinations; and yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 18.</note> have Chriſt's Righteouſneſſ impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them: For though we are not under the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law, ſo as to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to its Ordinances, diverſs Waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and <hi>Levitical</hi> Prieſt-hood, Chriſt our High-Prieſt having offer'd up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 20.</note> once for all, and aboliſh't it; yet are we not ſo under Grace, as to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from living well, though we are not tyed to its Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, yet are we obliged to fulfil its Righteouſneſs, which Chriſt came not to deſtroy but to eſtabliſh: For though<note place="margin">Ro. 3. 31. &amp; 8. 3, 4.</note> God be gracious and merciful to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our Treſpaſſes through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Chriſt, upon our true and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172527:10"/>
hearty repentance, and turning from<note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 7.</note> them; yet 'tis not that we ſhould take a libertyto go on in ſin &amp; rebellion againſt him. We are not to ſin becauſe he is gracious, that his Grace may abound;<note place="margin">Ro. 6. i. 2.</note> if ſo, Where is the ſtraitneſs of this way? If this be to take up a dayly Croſs to our own Wills that we may perform his, Pray where is the liberty of the fleſh? Thoſe that are vertually in Chriſt, which renders us acceptable to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and compleatly eſpouſed to him, muſt needs have reſigned their Wills, as an effect of true love, and requiſite to ſo ſtrict a union, oppoſite Wills be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inconſiſtent therewith, whence Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience neceſſarily follows. The Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> after having ſignified that God is Light, and that thoſe that would know the blood of cleanſing, and true fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1. 5. 7.</note> with him, and one another, ought to walk in the Light as he is in the Light, tells the young and weak in the Faith, whom he calls Children, that he writ thoſe things that they ſhould not ſin; but yet if any through weakneſs or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency ſhould ſin, and ſo fall under<note place="margin">Chap. 2. and firſt 6 Verſes.</note> the Fathers diſpleaſure, he tells them that Chriſt the Righteous is both a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation and alſo an Advocate that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceeds with the Father; and that their keeping his Commands was the ſureſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172527:11"/>
evidence of their knowing and being in him; but of the ſtrong, whom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he calls young men, he ſays, <hi>That the word of God abode in them, and that they had overcome the evil one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things may ſoon be ſpoken and comprehended in the Underſtanding, but to experience them fulfill'd in ourſelves, is our higheſt intereſt, and only can make us ſharers in them. The eſſence of Chriſtianity and happineſs of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, don't conſiſt in having our heads ſtuft with knowledge, only to lodge there and feed upon it, but to have our hearts filled with divine love, which ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates<note place="margin">Joh. 14. 21. 23.</note> us to diligence, and inſpires us with courage and vigor to obſerve and perform the Will of God, who looks not at what people profeſs only, or by what name they are call'd, but regards the heart, and what principle governs there: People may make a profeſſion of the beſt things; and yet continue alive to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they may alter Opinion or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and yet not turn from darkneſs to light, from the power of ſatan to God. There hath not been wanting a very large and ſplendid Profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, adorned with curious, elaborate, and elevated Notions, poliſh'd with Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick and Oratory; but that power and life that reaches the heart, and gives vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172527:11"/>
and dominion over its luſts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which war againſt the ſoul, is that which too many are yet ſtrangers to; when yet to know our lapſed ſouls reſtored from their firſt fallen ſtate in <hi>Adam,</hi> and raiſed to a ſtation where we may both perceive the things of God, and receive power to work his Will, to know our minds redeemed, and that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer vanquiſht which led us captive, and we leaven'd by the Heavenly Gift, into its own nature; as 'tis the very life and marrow of that Religion, about whoſe exteriour parts the world is filled with Noiſe; ſo 'tis the proper and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning-buſineſs of our lives, to find this great ſalvation accompliſh'd in us; the experimental working out whereof in the heart, by the ſaving Grace and Spirit<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 3, 4.</note> of God, that is given to man to profit with, will yield more ſatisfaction and true contentment to that ſoul that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely ſeeks the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Righteouſneſs thereof, in whom 'tis begun and carrying on, than to hear or read all their days of what God hath done through all Ages, for thoſe that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love and fear him; for want of which 'tis that the profeſſion of Chriſtianity is generally ſo empty &amp; barren in produc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a real pious life, attended with the fruits of the ſpirit, and a due Obedience proceeding from the birth of the ſpirit,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172527:12"/>
without which the moſt refined methods of Worſhip &amp; Devotion will not recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend us to God, who is inacceſſible <hi>by the birth of the Fleſh:</hi> Nor do we believe that 'tis acceptable to God for people to ſing before him thoſe Songs &amp; Pſalms, that were the experiencies and ſpiritual exerciſes of holy men in times paſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having ſome living experience of the ſame things in themſelves; or that People can properly and truly ſpeak more or farther of the things of God, than what they have known and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced. Where amongſt all theſe ſound Goſpel-Scriptural-Truths, is lodg'd that latent Venome ſo much fear'd and talk't of by our Adverſaries, that is ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly contagious, and apt to infect the minds of thoſe that ſhall incline to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Us, or our Books, touching our Belief in theſe neceſſary Points of Chriſtianity? Which of them is it, that being imbibed, is more mortal and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive<note place="margin">As ſaid <hi>Tho. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</hi>
               </note> to the ſoul, and defiles it more than drinking a draught of Poyſon, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Bawdy-houſe? Where are thoſe damnable Opinions and Hereſies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have been terrified? Which of them is it, that being perſiſted in, does neceſſorily lead to damnation, and for which the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>T. R's</hi> unſavory &amp; uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> 
               <hi>Devil muſt needs carry us a pick-pack to Hell?</hi> Is it in that we hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth the infinite Love of God to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172527:12"/>
in not only freely of his meer Grace and Favour, providing a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, thro' which an Atonement is made for the paſt Tranſgreſſions of man, who was never at all in a capacity to make any for himſelf, which is applicable to<note place="margin">Joh. 3. i5. 16. Act. 10. 43 1 Cor. 12. 7.</note> every one who ſhall believe, repent and return; but hath alſo afforded to all the means of Faith, Repentance and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for God requires not impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men, but expects they ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe talents diſtributed to them, in not only ſending forth the Son of his love to dye for their ſins, that they ſhould not longer live therein, but alſo in ſending<note place="margin">Joh. 14. i6, i7, 26. &amp; i6. i3. Tit. 2. ii, 12.</note> forth his Light and Spirit of Truth into their hearts, to lead and guide them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth, and cauſing his Grace that brings ſalvation, to appear to all men, to inſtruct and teach them to deny all Ungodlineſs and Worldly Luſts, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Devil and all his Works, the Pomps &amp; Vanities of this wicked World, to reſcue and ſave them from living in the ſinful Luſts of the Fleſh, and help and ſtrengthen them to return to their Obedience, and live a ſober, righteous and godly Life, to keep God's Holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the ſame all the days of their Lives.</p>
            <p>Which gift from God to man the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures plentifully teſtify to, under
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172527:13"/>
various denominations, as Spirit, Light, Word, Grace, Seed, Leaven, Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By all which we underſtand that Spirit or Heavenly Talent with which<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 14, 15.</note> God hath endowed Mankind in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or other that he may profit with it; in the improvement whereof by a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Co-working therewith, to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering thoſe holy ends for which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, we doubt not but to be happy in rendring a good account of our Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardſhip, and entring finally into the Joy of our Lord. Our oppoſers themſelves alſo pretend to the ſpirit and grace of God, or elſe what means their praying for its aſſiſtance, and thoſe plauſible fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpun diſcourſes of it, wherewith they ſometimes entertain their Auditory: We Charitably hope 'tis more real, than only to beautify and recommend them to the hearers, as what they cannot well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, for that the Scriptures are ſo full of that Language, and if indeed it be real, why is that a fault and error in us which is ſo ſound and ornamental in them? And we think it very ſtrange that they ſhould apprehend any incongruity in granting this Divine Principle to be a Divine Light to the mind; ſince its proper Office is to teach and Inſtruct, to manifeſt and point to us our duty, as well as to diſpoſe and enable us to perform it; and ought
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172527:13"/>
to be our leader and governour. If the<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12. Joh. 14. 17, 24. &amp; 16. 7, 8, 13, 14. 1 Joh. 2. 27.</note> godly admonitions, and exemplary lives of good men were rightly called lights to the world, ſurely much more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly may this, whoſe fountain is light, and does more nearly illuminate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the underſtanding, and renders thoſe effectual, juſtly challenge that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and acceptable appellation. If then the Grace and Spirit of God be in the hearts of men, ſurely 'tis not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unactive there, but will be making ſome attempts towards accompliſhing the end for which 'tis placed there; 'twill be at times attacking the enemies, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſupplant its contrary, which being holy and pure in its nature is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reconcileable to ſin and evil, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtrives againſt it, and may, as men regard, it be infallibly known by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its efforts. And we dare appeal even to all mankind, whether they find not ſomething placed in their minds and Conſciences, which though perhaps not regent there, yet never mingles with, nor Conſents to their evil deeds, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways remains undefiled, and teſtifies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and convicts, reproves, and<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 20, 21. Epheſ. 5. 13.</note> condemns them for it, and alſo oft-times in the cooler temper of their ſpirits, manifeſts their ſtates to them, and as 'twere reaſons with them, diſcovering
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172527:14"/>
the evil of their ways ſecretly calling to them to come out of it, begetting deſires and inclinations, ſometimes to ſeek after God, and to make their peace with him. Now ſince man in his meer natural State, is Totally dead and fallen from God, that he cannot as of himſelf think a good thought; and that God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is eſſentially good, and as that which is truly, ſo muſt needs proceed from him; this principle in us that ever convicts us<note place="margin">Joh. 16. 8, 13.</note> for vice and evil, whether in thought word or deed, and diſpoſeth us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of our latter end, and oft makes<note place="margin">Prov. 14. 13.</note> men ſigh in the midſt of laughter, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minding them, that for thoſe things they muſt give an account, that draws us heaven-ward and inclines us to vertue and goodneſs, to do to all men as we would be done unto, to be juſt, ſober, merciful, temperate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Muſt needs be ſomething that is not of us, but is pure and immaculate, and of a divine nature, ever <hi>aſpiring</hi> and raiſing the mind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its Original.</p>
            <p>Whence it cannot be a Natural Light or meer light of Nature, as very many would have it, who yet talk of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God being in Man, for 'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, that no agent can act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its own ſphere, and raiſe its object to a ſtate more noble than it ſelf, nor
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172527:14"/>
produce effects of a nature more ſublime<note place="margin">Job, 21. 17. Pſal. 18. 28.</note> than its own Original. Beſides 'tis very clear and evident from Scripture, that the mind of man is oft lighted by a light, Superiour to that of meer reaſon, and that man by the utmoſt power and extent of human reaſon &amp; ſpeculation, (though he may arrive to implicit knowledg that there is a God, yet) can never attain to a true, ſpiritual and ſaving knowledge of God, without the Concurrence of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine<note place="margin">Ro. 1. 19. 2 Cor. 4. 6. Prov. 20. 27. Luk. 24. 45. Joh. 1. 9. Epheſ. 5. 13, 14, 17.</note> and ſupernatural Agent: For though the mind of man as a rational Being, be that Capacity or Candle that is to be Lighted, yet 'tis Chriſt that muſt ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten it, as to give us a true diſcerning of thoſe things, that appertain to him and his Kingdom, and by adhering and yielding obedience to its diſcoveries, we ſhall know an Acceſſion of more Light.<note place="margin">Pſal. 369 Prov. 4. 18. 1 Cor. 2. 10. to the end.</note> And the Apoſtle ſpeaking of what God by his ſpirit had revealed to them, ſaith expreſly, that the ſpirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God; and that as none knows the things of a man, ſave the ſpirit of man which is in him, ſo the things of God knows no man but the ſpirit of God: That the natural man neither knoweth nor receiveth the things of the ſpirit of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and to that end they had received the ſpirit which is of God. The Light
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172527:15"/>
of Nature is occupied about natural Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, thoſe things that are within its own Region, acting within its own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Orb, but reaches not to that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God which is life eternal, except our natural powers or human capacity be illuminated by the rays of divine light,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 20.</note> for the world by humane wiſdom knows not God. And Chriſt ſaith very plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and poſſitively, that none knows the<note place="margin">Mat. 11. 27.</note> Father but the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him.</p>
            <p>That theſe ſtrugglings in us ſhould be the ſuggeſtions of Satan, that he ſhould diſquiet and diſturb people for their ſins, for ſerving him, and put them upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to be freed from their vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalage under his power, were abſurd to imagine; no, our Saviour puts that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a queſtion, when he asks, Can a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf ſtand?<note place="margin">Mark. 3. 24. 27.</note> And by and by ſaith plainly, that whilſt the ſtrong man arm'd keep the houſe his<note place="margin">Luk 11. 21</note> goods are at peace, till a ſtronger than he comes to bind him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that 'tis clear it's not the devil, but the approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of a ſuperiour power, that breaks the peace of people for ſin, and that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and condemns them for Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Trangreſſion, and is the ſame that would, and only can redeem their minds out of that miſerable ſtate, and bind that ſtrong man, and break his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172527:15"/>
power and caſt him out, would they but joyn thereto, and accept of deliverance by it.</p>
            <p>Nor does its being Extended to all men, through all Ages from their youth upwards, beſpeak it to be therefore natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or contemptible, but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of the greater moment to all men;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12 7.</note> for beſides that the Apoſtle ſaith a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the ſpirit is given to every man to profit withal, the bleſſings and gifts of God are free and valuable from their intrinſick worth; God in nature ordain'd nothing in vain, but by how much any thing is of the greateſt uſe to us, for ſuſtaining and accomodating our natural life, the more common it is, as the Sun that gives Light to all thro' all Ages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis we fondly rate things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our fancies, and eſteem and prize them more for their rarity and curioſity, than uſefulneſs; but God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows moſt univerſally that which is of the abſoluteſt neceſſity to man. Are not all men that are born, ſtrangers and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to God, in the dark, and at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from him in the State of Nature<note place="margin">Io. 3. 3. 5.</note> and muſt therefore be enlightned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and born again, and made ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual before we can be reconciled to him;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 3, 4. 2 Pet. 3. 9.</note> ſhall not God then, that would have all repent and be ſaved, cauſe the Light of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172527:16"/>
the Son of Righteouſneſs to ſhine upon all, and give a meaſure of his grace and ſpirit to all, to aſſiſt them in the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of that in themſelves which they cannot do of themſelves, and yet is of indiſpenſible neceſſity to our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Wherefore God by his ſpirit ſtrives with man ſo long as his day of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation laſts. Since then our oppoſers acknowledge the ſpirit and grace of God, which alſo is Light to be in Man, unleſs they can ſhew it, by its manifeſtly diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and ſuperiour nature, tendency, and operation, to be contradiſtinct from that we have been ſpeaking of; we ſee neither abſurdity nor error in conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be one and the ſame grace and free-gift of God to all, which is always the ſame in nature, though it differs in degree, and is that Heavenly Treaſure, which God hath committed to our truſt; and bleſſed will they be who rightly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy and improve it, and gives place and room to this ſeed of the Kingdom in<note place="margin">Mat. 13. 31. 32.</note> their hearts, where, though it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at firſt contrary to the expectation of man, little, mean and contemptable, ſcarcely regarded amongſt the ſtuff, wherewith mens minds are filled, yet joyn but to it, that it may exert its pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and force, and 'twill grow &amp; increaſe; let but this leaven have its perfect work
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172527:16"/>
and 'twill leaven the whole lump into its<note place="margin">Mat. 13. 33.</note> own nature.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to conſider, whether we have juſtly merited the invidious inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives of our adverſaries, in believing that the Lord ſearches the heart of man, and<note place="margin">Luk. 13. 21. Jer. 17. 10. Ro. 8. 27. Rev. 2. 23 Amos. 4. 13. Jer. 31. 33, 34. Ezek. 36. 26. 27. Joel, 2. 28, 29. Act. 2. i6, 17, 18. Iſa. 54. i3 Mat. 11. 27. Iſa. 42. 7. &amp; 61. 1.</note> ſhews him his thoughts, that he hath and will remember this latter age of the world, and hath not forgotten to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in performing thoſe bountiful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made in times paſt to the off-ſpring of the Gentiles, in placing his Law in our Hearts, and putting his truth in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, in pouring out of his ſpirit upon all the Sons and Daughters of men, in becoming our teacher, and giving us the knowledge of himſelf, through the Revelation of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, who is come to open our blind eyes, and to bring us, that were bound in darkneſs, out of the priſon-houſe, who hath promiſed to be with his people to the end of the World, in believing that God hath ſent<note place="margin">Joh. 14. 16, 17, 26. &amp; 16. 3.</note> us the Comforter, the ſpirit of Truth, to be our Remembrancer, and to guide and direct us in the way of Truth; in atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the ſufficiency and utility of the<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 20. 27.</note> Teachings of this Holy Unction, ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts, in believing that though Chriſt be in his glorified Body in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yet that he is preſent alſo in the hearts of his People, who is King of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172527:17"/>
Saints, and ſhall he not then rule in<note place="margin">Joh. 14. 17, 20, 23 &amp; 17. 23, 26. Iſa. 57. 15. 2 Cor. 6. 16. Prov. 8, 31.</note> them? The High and Holy One that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habits Eternity, hath promiſed to dwell alſo with the Humble and Contrite, to revive and comfort them, ſhall not he, whoſe preſence fills Heaven and Earth, be preſent in the Heart of Man? Shall not he that rejoyceth in the habitable parts of the Earth, and delights in the Sons of Men, reſide in his People? Are they not Members of him, and he their<note place="margin">Joh. 15. 4. 5.</note> Head? Can there be a more intimate Union and Communion than between the<note place="margin">1 Cor, 6. 15, 17, 19.</note> Head and the Body, the Vine and the Branches? The ſame Spirit of Life that is in the Head, is the Life of the Body alſo, and acts it; he that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit, doth not the Life that is in the Root paſs to the Branches alſo, and preſerves them living? Are not all dead Branches, in whom this Life is not? Whoſoever hath the Son of God, and feeds on him, hath Life by him; and<note place="margin">Joh. 6. 56, 57. 1 Joh. 5. 13.</note> thoſe that have not Chriſt, who is the Life of his Saints, hath not Life: How could his People in all Ages partake of him, if he were not preſent in them? Surely this Doctrine doth not deſerve to be ſcoft, but is moſt comfortable to thoſe<note place="margin">Ro. 10. 6, 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8. 2 Cor. 13. 5. Col. 2. 20</note> who are ſick of Love, and thirſt ardent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the Enjoyment [not Hear-ſay] of him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:172527:17"/>Conſider ſeriouſly theſe things which are agreeable to Scripture, and with what reaſon People have derided us for our Belief herein; terming it the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Chriſt, as though his manifeſting himſelf in our Hearts were another, or diſtinct from Jeſus Chriſt of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> that is glorified with God the Father in Heaven, which we deny: For though he be aſcended into Heaven, and ſits at<note place="margin">Col. 1. 16. Eph. 1. 23. &amp; 3. 9.</note> the right hand of God, far above all Principalities and Powers; yet is not he ſo circumſcribed, but that (as by him all things were made and created) he is the life, and filleth all in all in his Church and People. Is the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt divided? Is not their inſeparable Union the true and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Chriſt? Can then his God-head be preſent, and he who is the Heavenly Man be abſent? What think you of him that appear'd to <hi>John,</hi> and gave him his Commiſſion to the Seven Churches? whom he deſcribes, <hi>Rev. ch.</hi> 1. who ſaith, <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the door and knock, if any man hear my voice, and open the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 20. &amp; 2. 23.</note> 
               <hi>door, I will come in to him, and will ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> The ſame ſaith, <hi>I am he which ſearches the reins and hearts, and I will give unto every one of you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172527:18"/>
according to your works:</hi> Was not this<note place="margin">Acts 17. 31. Rom. 2. 16. John 1. 16.</note> the true Chriſt the Mediator, by whom God will judge the World? And can he make this near Inſpection into the innermoſt part of the Minds of Men, ſo as no Thought can eſcape his notice, if he be not preſent there? What made <hi>Paul</hi> deſire that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt<note place="margin">1 John 4. 13.</note> might be with <hi>Timothy</hi>'s Spirit, if he thought it impoſſible? Do not all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Spirit of Chriſt, who is the Anointed, to be in his People, and is he then abſent? Is its being a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, far beyond our comprehenſion to conceive how it can be a ſufficient Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that therefore 'tis not ſo? Ought we not in ſuch caſes to exerciſe Faith? and acquieſs in the Teſtimony of the Holy Ghoſt, expreſt in the Sacred Scriptures, rather than interpoſe with our nice and curious Subtilties? pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unneceſſarily into things that are too high for us; remembering that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Things belongs to God; and that thoſe that know moſt here, know only in part the things that are inviſible;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 9, 12.</note> and ſee them but as through a Glaſs. Shall Men that neither know themſelves, nor have any intuitive knowledge of the Eſſences, even of the meaneſt things,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172527:18"/>
wherewith Nature every-where preſents us, which are obvious to our Senſes; yet aſpire to thoſe more abſtruce, and undertake to account for that which is beyond the reach of the moſt pregnant Wits to penetrate.</p>
            <p>We hope it's no Error to avouch the Power of Chriſt to be ſtronger than that of the Devil, that he is able really to<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note> bind him, to bruiſe his Head, and break his Power, to diſpoſſeſs and caſt him out, to fulfil to the uttermoſt the end of his coming, to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, and to ſave thoſe from their ſins who ſhall have true Faith in his Name and Power: Surely it's not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Chriſtianity to believe that Chriſt can, or will, throughly purge his Floor; that he can indeed deliver out of<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 23.</note> the Priſon-houſe, and reſtore Man out of the Fall to God again, and give him power to forſake the Devil and all his Works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We find it conſonant to Scripture, and the Goſpel-diſpenſation, to believe that thoſe who are regenerated and<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 6, 7, 11. 2 Pet. 1. 4.</note> born again of the Spirit, have through the Spirit mortified the firſt carnal cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature, which cannot pleaſe God,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172527:19"/>
and if dead, and ſlain, and buried too,<note place="margin">Eph. c. 4. v. 22, 23, 24. Coloſ. c. 3. v. 9. 10.</note> ſurely then it no longer lives, but the mind is at liberty, and reſtored to act in a new Life, to walk after the Spirit, and fulfil the Righteouſneſs of the Law; the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 2, 4.</note> Jeſus, having ſet them free from the Law of Sin, and Death which is its Wages. 'Tis for want of Peoples expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riencing this real Birth of the Spirit brought forth, and knowing Freedom in themſelves by it, which no Duties or Performances in the Will of Man, nor entertaining of the moſt reſined Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in Religion can adminiſter, ſhort of the Law of the Spirit of Chriſt in their hearts; 'tis for want of this, that People are ſo very apprehenſive, of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, even to impoſſibility, of living a Holy Righteous Life; which yet is ſo neceſſary to our Salvation, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<note place="margin">Mat. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8. Heb. 12. 14.</note> it we cannot enter the Kingdom of Heaven, nor ſee God. Nor is the way broader, or its paſſage leſs ſtrait and difficult than they imagine; nay, 'tis abſolutely impoſſible for them to walk therein, while they are immerc'd in their firſt corrupt unbridled Nature, which cannot keep the Law of God, while their Luſts and Paſſions are ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172527:19"/>
their Affections inordinate, and Wills unſubjected, and follows the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and evil inclinations of their Minds without reſtraint. But if they come to know another Principle and Power to govern their Minds, to create in them new clean Hearts, to regulate and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject their Wills, to ſubdue and tame their Paſſions, to limit their Deſires, and direct their Affections and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wholly after that which is good, to meliorate their Spirits throughout, and make them heavenly minded, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an averſion to all Evil, and a great love to Vertue and Goodneſs: Being thus perfectly transformed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where is the extream difficulty now, for the good Man, out of the good treaſure of his<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 35.</note> Heart, to bring forth good things? Will not this new well-inclin'd inſide, that now deteſts Evil, and loves and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in Righteouſneſs, as naturally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after, and bring forth that which is Good, as before he did Evil? Here is no force upon Peoples Natures, but they are converted, and throughly lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened in another Nature, and are in their meaſures Partakers of the Divine Nature, which only can work the Will<note place="margin">2 Pet. 4.</note> of God. We requeſt our piouſly-incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172527:20"/>
Neighbours, well and ſeriouſly to weigh and conſider, the abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there is for every True Chriſtian thus to know; their minds moulded and<note place="margin">Col. 1. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> faſhioned anew, by the Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, working mightily in them, in order to their pleaſing God by a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Righteous Life, having eſcaped the corruption that is in the World through Luſt; and conſidering that 'tis not ſo ſoon attained, as apprehended in the underſtanding to be neceſſary: That with all diligence they addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the performing that which is the main and proper buſineſs of our Lives. Wherefore as it hath pleaſed the Divine Power to give us all things pertaining to Life and Godlineſs, ſo let<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 3. Tit. 2. 11, 12. Phil 2. 12, 13.</note> us with a vigilant attention to, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working with that Grace, which to that end is given, work out our Salvation with a reverend fear; ſince a good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of attainment herein is ſoon loſt, except there be a conſtant ſedulous watchfulneſs upon the Mind amidſt all buſineſs and concerns, to have a check upon our words and thoughts, and a diligent preſſing forward: For while<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 41.</note> we live in this World we are liable to temptations, and may enter thereinto
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172527:20"/>
alſo, without a ſtrict care and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; our Senſes preſenting many baits to our Minds on every hand, which Satan makes uſe of to beguile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and many provocations offer themſelves in<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 9.</note> our Pilgrimage; againſt all which God's Grace is ſufficient Armour; as our Minds are ſeaſoned by it, ſo that where any ſhortneſs is, 'tis through Inſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Negligence, or Inadvertency</p>
            <p>Or is it a dangerous heinous Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie that we with very many Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, believe the Univerſality of<note place="margin">Pſ. 145. 9.</note> the Love of God to all Mankind; that God who is good to all, whoſe Mercies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to all the Works of his Hands; is ſincere in his Intention, and Atteſtation thereof, and doth not deſign to delude<note place="margin">Ezek. 33. 11. &amp; 18. 23.</note> us, when he affirms, That as certainly as he lives he deſires not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he would return and live; that God, whoſe Love and Mercy is unlimited, doth graciouſly and<note place="margin">John c. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> v. 14 15, 16, 17. Iſai. 55. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Rev. 22. 17. Rom. 5. 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> generouſly offer Salvation, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, (upon certain Conditions to be performed on our part) to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to every individual Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man upon the face of the Earth, which is the true Goſpel-meſſage, good Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings<note place="margin">Luke 2. 10, 14.</note> of great Joy, which ſhall be to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172527:21"/>
all People, Peace on Earth, and good will towards Men; good cauſe indeed to rejoyce, that all are within the verge<note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 7. Ezek. c. 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> v<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22, to the end.</note> of Mercy and free Pardon; that God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no Reſpecter of Perſons, but among all Nations and People, he or ſhe that fears him, and works Righteouſneſs is<note place="margin">Acts 10. 34, 35. 1 Joh. 2. 2. Heb. 2. 9.</note> of him accepted; and that Chriſt dyed for the ſins of the whole World, yea, for every Man; ſurely then all for whom he dyed are thereby put into a capacity for Salvation; that ſaving<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11.</note> Grace hath appeared to all Men, and a<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 7. See Pro. c. 1. from v. 20. to the end.</note> manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every Man to profit withal. And that none are reprobated, but thoſe that continue to be deaf to the Calls of this Grace, and reſiſts the Spirit, and hides and neglects their Talents till the day<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 37.</note> of their Viſitation be over; and Chriſt ſo withdraws himſelf, as to ceaſe lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſtrive with them; ſo that the<note place="margin">Neh. 9. 20, 26.</note> means being taken away, they are left to themſelves, and given up to Hardneſs<note place="margin">Iſa. 63. 10. Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 81. v. 11, 12, 13.</note> of Heart; that being abſent that ſhould prepare, tender, and mollifie it, that now they cannot Repent, Believe, and be Converted.</p>
            <p>If thus to believe be a dangerous and pernitious Errour, we confeſs we are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172527:21"/>
Guilty, and not like to be otherwiſe; for we cannot perſwade ourſelves to embrace that Anti-evangelical Opinion, That God from all Eternity hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally and conditionally, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their accepting or rejecting the Salvation offer'd in Chriſt, elected ſome and reprobated others by an immutable Decree, ſo that thoſe who are ſo elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall certainly be ſaved, let them do what they will, for God's Decree can't be reverſs'd, let the unſtable Mind of Man vary as it will: and thoſe that are reprobated were in effect damned thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Years before they were born, ſo that their Salvation is put beyond all hope, let them ſeek it never ſo eareſtly and diligently, and be never ſo deſirous to ſerve and pleaſe God. For beſides, that this ſad Tidings inſtead of glad Tidings, if it were really true in itſelf, puts an end to the whole buſineſs of Religion, by rendring all Worſhip and Devotion, all Preaching, Praying, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling together, and Holy Living as 'twere uſeleſs, by invalidating all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever on Man's part, as nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing (as a neceſſary Condition on his part to be performed or neglected) towards his Salvation or eternal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172527:22"/>
We dare not take up an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſo diametrically oppoſite to the very Attributes of God, and his repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Proteſtations to the contrary, and with ſome Men thus preſume to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign his Juſtice, Mercy and Goodneſs; we cannot believe that God who is Love itſelf, and Goodneſs itſelf, and hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways manifeſted a wonderful Care and Concern for Man as his darling Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">VViſ. 12. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16.</note> it being diſagreeable to his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to condemn thoſe that have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be puniſhed, and having no pleaſure in the death of him that dies,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18. 22. VViſ. 11. 23, 24.</note> ſhould yet make the major part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind with deſign to damn them, unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd thereto, without ever tendring them Salvation; or that he would make the far greater number wholly uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of accepting the Salvation tendred them, by putting it out of their power to perform thoſe Conditions and Terms upon which he offers it, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them to eternal Miſery for not complying with thoſe Conditions that 'twas impoſſible for them to obſerve: For he don't only call to all the ends of<note place="margin">Iſai. 45. 22.</note> the Earth (which implies all Mankind) to look to him and be ſaved, but he hath given to every one a Portion of his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172527:22"/>
Spirit to enable them ſo to do, he hath not only ſent forth the Son of his Love<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 14, 15, 16.</note> to ſhed his Blood for every Man, to be lifted up as <hi>Moſes</hi> lifted up the Brazen Serpent, that whoſoever believeth in<note place="margin">Joh. 6. 44, 45.</note> him ſhould not periſh; but he alſo draws them, and as they will receive it, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them with that Divine Magnet that only can incline and impower them ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to turn to that Pole in which all our true Happineſs centers.</p>
            <p>But this is the condemnation, that<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19, 20.</note> light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 13.</note> their deeds are evil; and hates the light, and will not bring their deeds to it, leſt it ſhould reprove them; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is reprovable is made manifeſt by the light, but men love their own broad ways, to purſue the ſight of their eyes and deſire of their minds, and<note place="margin">Eccl. 11. 9.</note> therefore hate to be control'd therein and reform'd. The Apoſtle ſtirring up the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to Purity of Life, and to avoid ſeveral Evils there mentioned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaith expreſly, <hi>Let no man deceive you</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>with vain words, for becauſe of theſe things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of diſobedience.</hi> And in another place, <hi>That</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 13.</note> 
               <hi>thoſe who live after the fleſh ſhall die.</hi> So
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172527:23"/>
that 'tis for want of Peoples embracing the Means, and bringing their Deeds to the Light of Chriſt in their Hearts, and heeding the Reproofs of Inſtruction,<note place="margin">Prov. 6. 23. Gal. 6. 8.</note> which is the Way of Life, for want of ſowing to the Spirit, and by it mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Deeds of the Fleſh, that People are loſt and ſentenced to Perdition, and not becauſe they were perſonally and inconditionally reprobated from all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. God who is Lord of all, is<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 3, 4.</note> gracious unto all, and would have all Men to be ſaved; but they diſobey the Call of God, and reject his Offers, and reſiſt the Strivings of his Spirit, and are deaf to thoſe Knocks of our Saviour for Reception and Entertainment in their<note place="margin">Rev. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 20.</note> Hearts, and chuſe and prefer the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World, and will not deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to follow Chriſt. 'Tis not as theſe Men ſay, becauſe Salvation was never within their reach: if 'twere not, what muſt we think? Were thoſe feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tears then that our Saviour ſhed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<note place="margin">Luke 16. 41, 42. Matth. 23. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when the Day of its Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was over? Saying alſo, <hi>How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten would I have gathered thee as a hen ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers her chickens, but you would not;</hi> not you could not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:172527:23"/>If any Men can be ſo hardy as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain an Opinion ſo derogatory to the Juſtice, Mercy, Love, and Paternal Care of God, and repugnant to the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſage, we cannot but admire what ſhould induce them to obtrude it upon others, and urge it as though 'twas a neceſſary Point to be believed in the Chriſtian Religion; for we cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend how this begets love to God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth Faith in Chriſt, and raiſeth our Veneration for him, excites to Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and encourages Piety, which is that which advanceth true Religion; but on the contrary, that it tends to the indulging ſome in a Security, and procure in others a ſlight Eſteem of the Death and Sacrifice of Chriſt, as being partial, and caſts them into Deſpond, and probably may encourage both to gratifie the Deſires of their Minds to the full extent, ſince nothing can alter ſuch a ſuppoſed Decree of God one way or the other: Yet we deny not the Preſcience of God, who fore-knows all things, things paſt, preſent, and to come, being at once preſent to him; ſo that it may be ſaid, ſuch who believe in Chriſt with that living active Faith that works by Love, and excites to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:172527:24"/>
and perſevere therein unto the end, and ſo knows Salvation by him, are in him in whom the Election is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World began; and that thoſe who ſo believe not, but reject the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his Love, and by perſiſting in Diſobedience, neglects ſo great Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are condemned already. Nor do we deny ſuch a Preference as that ſome are made Stewards over more, and ſome fewer Talents, according to which their Improvement ought to be: Where much is given much is required, and where leſs is given leſs is required; for God is juſt and equal in all his Ways, he is not a hard Maſter, that he ſhould exact<note place="margin">Matth. 25. 14, to the 28.</note> or expect more than the Improvement of his own: Had he that received but one Talent, imploy'd it, and made it two, we doubt not but it had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; for we believe that none are from Eternity abſolutely excluded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Talent, and that a Day alſo is afforded wherein 'tis poſſible for them to improve it. So that though the Grace may work more powerfully in ſome than in others, yet are all left without Excuſe.</p>
            <p>There is yet another Opinion depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on this, which we cannot receive
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172527:24"/>
neither, as they ſtate it, for which our Oppoſers think very ill of us; that is, once in a ſtate of Grace and ever ſo; that there is no total or final falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from Grace. How this Doctrine promotes true Zeal and Piety, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves Chriſtianity, we can't underſtand, nor ſee no other reaſon why its Votaries ſhould be ſo fond of it, but becauſe 'tis concordant to that of Perſonal Election and Reprobation; ſo that thoſe who imbrace the one, are bound to believe the other: But otherwiſe, certainly it tends rather to ſlacken than ſpur on People to that care and diligence, and conſtant unwearied watchfulneſs to Prayer, which our Lord ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to, and the Apoſtles ſo ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly preſſes the Saints every-where to be found in, as of abſolute neceſſity. What elſe means thoſe Promiſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> to thoſe who ſhould overcome and hold out to the end, but to ingage them to a conſtant Perſeverance? Or what needed it, if 'twere impoſſible for them to fall ſhort; who I ſuppoſe none will deny to have been in a ſtate of Grace? And the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was threatned to<note place="margin">Rev. 2. 5. 3. 16.</note> have their Candleſtick removed, if they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172527:25"/>
repented not, and did their firſt works; and that of <hi>Laodicea</hi> to be ſpewed out of his Mouth. Who can ſay thoſe fooliſh Virgins in the Parable were not once in a ſtate of Grace, whoſe Lamps were once lighted and burning, as well as trimm'd, or elſe they could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to be gone out; Or that thoſe were not call'd by Saving Grace,<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 8.</note> in whoſe hearts the Heavenly Seed ſprung up, and for a time proſper'd,<note place="margin">Luke c. 8. v. 7, 8, 14, 15.</note> 'till the Bryars and Thorns, the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care and concern about the things of this Life, choak'd it; 'twas not that they had no day of Viſitation from God, wherein they might have wrought out their Salvation, had they continued to make the Kingdom of Heaven, and its Righteouſneſs, their firſt and chiefeſt Choice, and placed their treaſure there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and diſentangled themſelves from thoſe unneceſſary Cares; the Seed that was ſown and ſprung up, was the very ſame with that which in the honeſt heart brought forth fruit abundantly.</p>
            <p>Surely <hi>Paul</hi> that Great Apoſtle was not of theſe Mens Opinion, when after he had long laboured in the Goſpel, takes care to keep under his Body, leaſt<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 27.</note> while he Preach'd to others he himſelf
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:172527:25"/>
ſhould be a Caſt-away, whom yet we doubt not, but they will grant was then effectually called, and in a ſtate of Grace. And the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> writing in the third Chapter, to thoſe he calls holy Brethren, and Partakers of the heavenly Calling, Verſe the 12th, exhorts them to take heed leſt there was in any of them an evil Heart of Unbelief in departing from the Living God. And again, Chap. 4. 1. <hi>Let us therefore fear lest a promiſe being left us of entring his rest,</hi> (ſurely then not eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally reprobated) <hi>any of you ſhould ſeem to come ſhort of it.</hi> Verſe 12. <hi>Let us la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour therefore to enter that rest, lest any man fall after the ſame example of unbelief.</hi> Again <hi>Chap. 6. Verſe</hi> 4, 5, 6. ſpeaking of thoſe who had been enlightned, and had taſted of the heavenly Gift, and were made Partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and that had taſted the good Word of God, and the Powers of the World to come, (ſhew'd ſigns that they were ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually call'd, and in a State of Grace) that if they ſhould fall away 'twould be impoſſible to renew them again to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; not becauſe they were eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally reprobated, but becauſe they cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to themſelves the Son of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172527:26"/>
becauſe they grieved his good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18. 24, 26. and c. 33. v. 18.</note> and rejected the Means: Hath not the Lord ſaid, If a righteous man turns from his righteouſneſs, he ſhall die: Who can be righteous without the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of God's Grace? No Man can make himſelf ſo; 'tis not in Man to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his own Ways; and yet it ſeems 'tis poſſible for him to fall from it, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath lived ſo long under its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct as by it to be made righteous, and one would think ſhould then be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied too. Our Saviour ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>I am the true vine, ye are the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1, 2, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>my Father is the husband-man, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry branch in me that beareth not fruit he taketh away.</hi> Again, <hi>If a man abide not in me, he is cast forth as a branch and is withered.</hi> Surely thoſe who are Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in Chriſt, while ſo, are accepted of the Father; and yet it ſeems 'tis poſſible for them to fall away and be cut off as wither'd Branches; whence he often repeats this Condition if ye abide in me; and preſently he ſaith<note place="margin">John 15. 10.</note> the way to continue in his Love was to do his Will, as he had that of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's, and continued in his Love. But though we can't embrace their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for their Reaſons, and as they ſtate
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:172527:26"/>
it, but that 'tis poſſible for People to make a conſiderable Progreſs in Grace, and yet for want of a careful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Watchfulneſs to that Grace they may fall away: Yet we believe ſuch a State and Growth in Grace throw a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant Attention thereto, and ſuch a degree of Faith attainable, as that there is no more going forth.</p>
            <p>But that which ſeems to be our capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Error, and the top of all their Charge, and that which is to ſilence all Plea's in our behalf, is our omitting the uſe of the Ordinances (ſo called) of Baptiſm and Bread, and Wine. <hi>John</hi> indeed as the next immediate Fore-runner of Chriſt to prepare his Way, gave an Alarm to the <hi>Jews</hi> that were ſo ſecure under the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and proclaim'd the Kingdom of Heaven at hand, and<note place="margin">Mat. 3. 2. Acts 17. 30.</note> the time come wherein, God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Jews,</hi> as well as others every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where to repent; 'twas not ſufficient for them to go on in ſinning, and then offer thoſe reſpective Sacrifices which the Law enjoyn'd them for the ſame, but now the Wrath of God was near<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 18.</note> to be reveal'd from Heaven againſt all Ungodlineſs and Unrighteonſneſs of Men: 'twas not ſufficient to deek and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172527:27"/>
make clean the outſide of the Cup and<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 25, 26. and c. 3. 10.</note> Platter, but the inſide was to be clean'd, and then the outſide would be clean alſo. The Axe was now laid to the root, and every Tree that brought not forth good Fruit was to be hewn down. The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> took hold on exterior Acts and could not make perfect as pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Heb. 9. 9. 2 Cor. 10. 5. James 1. 15.</note> to the Conſcience, but now that Diſpenſation was about to be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that comes nearer home, and takes cognizance of the very Thoughts, that Sin be not ſo much as conceived by the Will's joyning thereto. Wherefore <hi>John</hi> was ſent to adminiſter the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Repentance as a lively Figure of that which was preſently after to follow; for <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm was not capable to produce this Effect upon the Mind: and he himſelf teſtifies, <hi>That though he baptized them with water, yet he that came after him, that was before him, and more honourable than he, ſhould baptize them with the Holy Ghoſt, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. c. 3. v. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12.</note> 
               <hi>with fire, that his fan was in his hand, and and that 'twas he ſhould throughly purge his floor.</hi> Which is the great Work that is to be done under his Goſpel-diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to take away the Sins of the World, and deſtroy the Works of the<note place="margin">1 John 3. 8.</note>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:172527:27"/>
Devil, to purifie Peoples Hearts, and make them ſpiritually minded; this is the proper Effects of Chriſt's laſting Baptiſm, not the waſhing away of the Filth of the Fleſh, but the anſwer of a<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 21.</note> good Conſcience towards God, to purge our Conſciences from dead Works, to ſerve the Living God in Newneſs of Life. The Baptiſm of Chriſt is but<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 5. Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. 3. and v. 6, 7, 8, 11.</note> one, and thoſe who by it are baptized into Jeſus Chriſt, are baptized into his Death, and their old Man crucified with him, that the body of Sin may be deſtroy'd, and they no longer ſerve Sin, becauſe they that are dead with Chriſt are freed from Sin, and made alive to God, to live a holy righteous Life: Theſe are the bleſſed Effects of the Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt and Fire, and Benefits that redound to thoſe who are in truth waſhed by Chriſt in that holy Laver which entitles us to a part<note place="margin">Zech. 13. 1.</note> in him; 'tis our chiefeſt Concern to know this inward ſpiritual Baptiſm of Chriſt, that our Hearts may be waſhed,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11.</note> purified, and ſanctified by the Spirit of God; and that we really put on Chriſt, and are in him who is the Subſtance, in whom the Types ended. <hi>John</hi> knew and foretold himſelf that he muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:172527:28"/>
but Chriſt muſt encreaſe; he<note place="margin">John 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 30.</note> doth not ſay, I ſhall ceaſe preſently at once, ſo ſoon as Chriſt's Baptiſm takes place; but I muſt decreaſe, but were Water-baptiſm to continue always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, then would not <hi>John</hi> decreaſe: Nor will it ſolve this Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That 'twas aboliſht as <hi>John</hi>'s, and inſtituted anew as Chriſt's, for then hath Chriſt his different Goſpel-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms, which is erronious.</p>
            <p>We grant that ſome of the Apoſtles did uſe Water-baptiſm for a time, but we believe 'twas rather in compliance with the Circumſtances of Time than of Neceſſity, and in condeſcention to the Weakneſs of Believers in the very Infancy of the Church, and even the ſame Age wherein <hi>John</hi> baptized, who was not only a true Meſſenger of God in his time, but had gained great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit among the People, and his Memory and Meſſage could not ſoon be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; nor was it eaſie to draw them from a Practice that but juſt before was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be of Divine Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for we find the Apoſtles tolerated the believing <hi>Jews</hi> to live in certain Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law, notwithſtanding the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:172527:28"/>
come in the Fleſh and abrogated them; ſo difficult 'tis to diſengage People from thoſe things wherein they have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated, and to which their Minds are once glewed, and ſome of them would have had the believing Gentiles come under that Yoak and be circumciſed, which <hi>Paul</hi> their great Apoſtle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſeeing beyond all thoſe things, knowing that the Kingdom of God was not Meats and Drinks, but Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 17.</note> Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not in Word but Power,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 20.</note> not divers Waſhings and carnal Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which were Shadows and to<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. v. 14 &amp; 16, 17, 22, 10. Heb. 9. 9, 10. Gal. 5. 2.</note> perriſh, but the Body is of Chriſt, and thoſe that are in him, are in him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, believing that if they were cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing; and yet we ſee ſuch was his Condeſcention, that he himſelf not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> and when he was at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhaved his<note place="margin">Acts c. 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> v. 20, to the 28.</note> head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> behaving himſelf as a <hi>Jew,</hi> for the ſakes of thoſe who ſaw not ſo far as himſelf. And notwithſtanding he was ſuch a labourious and zealous Publiſher of the Goſpel, yet we find<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 14.</note> he baptized but very few, and thanks God that he baptized no more, (ſurely
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:172527:29"/>
'twas not then eſſential to the Goſpel) but ſaith plainly, That he was not<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 17. Coloſ. 1. 13.</note> ſent to baptize, but to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to turn People from Darkneſs to Light, from the Power of Satan to God, who had delivered them from the Power of Darkneſs, and tranſlated them into the Kingdom of his dear Son; 'tis this that is of abſolute Neceſſity to our Salvation: he did not then baptize be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome others did it, which yet is as large a Commiſſion as perhaps any pretend to now-a-days Of which we ſay as he did of Circumciſion (though we do not grant 'tis the Seal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and introduced in room of Circumciſion as ſome will have it, but without Scripture-authority) Baptiſm or no Baptiſm availeth any thing ſhort of a new Creature, which is the trueſt Sign of poſſeſſing the inward ſpiritual Grace, and of being in Chriſt, and is beyond all viſible Signs whatſoever: The Apoſtles having thus indulged it, 'tis no wonder that 'twas continued, and ſince got footing under the Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy, for as Corruption entred the Church, and was encreaſed, the Spirit and Life of Chriſtianity was more and more eclipſed, and the minds of its
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:172527:29"/>
Profeſſors grew darker, and then adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more to external Performances; and not only continued that which had been uſed by their Predeceſſors, or at leaſt ſomething in its ſtead, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees added more Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; and at length began to trim and deck that Religion that in itſelf was plain, ſimple, and homely, and conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more in Power and Divine Love than outward Obſervations; which in proceſs of time was ſo dreſt and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, that its Auguſt Splendour became inviting to others. Under this Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy in degree ſprung up Infant-Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, a meer Humane Invention, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Scripture-authority either by Precept or Practice; wherefore for thoſe who do not uſe Baptiſm, as 'twas inſtituted under its proper Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to upbraid us for neglecting it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furd and unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>But that which makes the loudeſt Out-cry of all, is our Diſuſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſo called of Bread and Wine, 'tis this is that peſtilent mortal Error that in our Oppoſer's Account, renders us worſe then the Papiſts, whatever 'tis that makes us the Spawn of the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, which with ſeveral others are Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thets,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:172527:30"/>
that to be ſure were calculated tho' unjuſtly to render us as odious as may be to the People, and carry a great deal of Rancour in them, and ſavours of too much Gall, to proceed from the meek Spirit of Chriſtianity,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 22.</note> that teacheth to be at Peace with, and have Charity for all that call on the Lord out of a pure heart: But whether up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Matter we deſerve this ſevere bitter Cenſure, or whether thoſe that ſo liberally beſtows it upon us, have a juſt right to caſt the firſt Stone, is what we deſire our ſober Neighbours to conſider, and not judge us alſo by whole-ſale, from an implicit Belief of what others ſay of us. We are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantof the great Noiſe and Stir there hath been about this in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to the ſcandalizing Chriſtianity among both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks:</hi> the Papiſts have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd it to downright Idolatry, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming 'tis the real Body and Blood, and as ſuch adores it, (one would think 'twere better let alone) others, that Chriſt is in it, though they know not how: one ſaith 'tis this, another 'tis that; while they all ſeem to expect that from it which it doth not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily adminiſter; for want of diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:172527:30"/>
between that Bread of Life that<note place="margin">John 6. 51, 56.</note> came down from Heaven, that Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt, which giveth Life to all that feed thereon, by which they dwell in him and he in them, and that Supper which was eaten by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians in Commemoration of his Death and Sacrifice; which are not ſo connext, as that the one neceſſarily includes the other, as Experience abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly teſtifies, would People but be true to themſelves herein; how many are there that receive this from Year to Year, who yet complain all their lives of Deadneſs, Dryneſs, and Leanneſs of Soul, and want of Power, not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that renewing of Life and ſpiritual Strength that is propoſed in it, and ſo but an empty Shadow indeed: for how can they in truth expect to feed on<note place="margin">John 14. 20, 21, 23.</note> Chriſt ſpirituallyin their Hearts who will not admit that he really dwells in his Saints, but eſteem it an Error in thoſe that do; however, we believe all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ought to be well perſwaded in their own Minds, and ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in theſe and other religious Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, and not take up things meerly tradititionally becauſe others do it; nor ought they to be vehemently preſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:172527:31"/>
to or againſt things not abſolutely eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Salvation, in which their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings are not clear: nor ſhould any be ſcoft or reproacht for thoſe things which to them are Matter of Conſcience, and therefore Sacred, though to others it may appear of leſs moment; a Practice that is a great Shame among People profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. Nor do we judge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe that are found in the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice either of this or Water-baptiſm as 'twas primitively uſed, whoſe ſober, Chriſtian, circumſpect Lives witneſſeth to their ſincere Intentions herein, who may be conſcientiouſly tender in it, and fearful to omit it, till they are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fully perſwaded: But for us, to whom the barrenneſs and emptineſs of theſe outward viſible Things are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, we cannot continue therein, yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no true Soul-ſatisfaction, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring any inward ſpiritual Grace to us. Wherefore having taſted that<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 2, 3.</note> the Lord is good and gracious, we wait for the ſincere Milk of that Word by which we have been begotten to God, that we may receive ſtrength thereby, and grow in Grace, and the Knowledge<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 18.</note> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and a greater
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:172527:31"/>
Acquaintance with that true inward Spiritual Communion and Fellowſhip<note place="margin">Rev. 3. 20.</note> with him, wherein he ſups with his Saints, and they with him; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Life by him, who dwells in them,<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 30.</note> and they in him; as the Members are joyned to the Head, and partakes of its Life, and liveth by it; or the Branches to the Vine, which receives<note place="margin">Joh. 15. 5.</note> Life, Vertue and Nouriſhment from him, whereby Fruit is brought forth to the glory of God, and well-pleaſing to him. 'Tis not ſufficient that we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate hereof once a Month or Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but as the <hi>Jews</hi> had their Manna,<note place="margin">Exod. 16. 21.</note> freſh every Morning, ſo ought we to receive a daily ſupply, and renewing of ſtrength in our inward Man, by eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Heavenly Bread, that nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up to Eternal Life, and drinking plentifully of that Well of Living-We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Joh. 4. 14.</note> which in the Saints ſprings up to Life Eternal; for as in God we live, move, and have our very being; ſo is Chriſt the true and proper Life of the inward Man by which it truly lives to God, nor can it live but by him. Thoſe that are begotten to God by the Word of Life, and are born again of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are priviledged thus to feed on
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:172527:32"/>
Chriſt, and enjoy him, which none can do that are not firſt quickened and made alive by him; none can receive Life, Sap and Vertue from him as Head and Vine, that are not firſt joyned to him as Members and Branches of him; nor is it ſufficient to make People Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and give them admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to feed on him, in that they were ſprinkled when Infants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as we have already expreſs'd, though they ſhould eat Bread and drink Wine all their days.</p>
            <p>Since then we no leſs enjoy the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance without the Sign, why may we not omit it, as either being but tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, or not of abſolute neceſſity, as well as our Oppoſers do that which was inſtituted (to uſe their own term) at the ſame time, and with as great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, and greater formality, and was no leſs poſitively commanded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame pretence? Why may not the ſame Authority abſolve us from the uſe of this, and excuſe us from being chargeable with the breach of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, as releaſe them from waſhing one anothers Feet, and ſecure<note place="margin">Joh. 13. 4, 5, 8, 14, 15.</note> them from the like cenſure? As alſo that of the Apoſtles, cencerning things
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:172527:32"/>
ſtrangled and Blood, and that of <hi>James</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15. 20, 29. Jam. 5. 14, 15.</note> anointing the Sick with Oil? Why ſhould they be thus partial? Have we not good reaſon to conclude, that if theſe had not been long ſince laid down, they would have cleav'd as cloſe to them; and that had thoſe of Baptiſm, and Bread and Wine been then diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued alſo, they would be now as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie under its omiſſion? For Tradition, Cuſtom, and Education, makes greater impreſſions on Mens minds than per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps every one may be ſenſible of; nor is it an eaſie task at firſt to move them from thoſe things to which they have been faſtned by it. Would but People wholly relinquiſh theſe Prejudices, and conſider it impartially, 'tis probable there may appear no ſuch real diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as juſtly to omit the one, and yet with equal reaſon to continue the other; ſince 'tis not that Bread that gives life to the Soul, nor doth neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily include it, but that Chriſt may be, and is received, and ſed on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. Nor that thoſe can be thought to forget his Death and Sacrifice who ſenſibly partake of the Benefits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 14.</note> and purſue its Ends; who are taught and aſſiſted by him to live a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 4.</note>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:172527:33"/>
righteous Life, and bears about in them the Marks of the Dying of our<note place="margin">Mat. 1. 21. 2 Cor. 5. 15.</note> Lord Jeſus; who died for all, that thoſe who live ſhould no longer live to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, fulfilling the deſires of their minds, but to him that died for them; that through the power of his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 10.</note> they may mortifie the Deeds of the Fleſh, and have Fellowſhip with his Sufferings, in whom his Life is made manifeſt; neither can thoſe who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his Death and Sacrifice, and partake from time to time of this Bread and Wine in memory of it, and yet are not by him redeemed from a vain Converſation, and made conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Death, and ſo feed on him as to participate of that Life that comes by him, in anywiſe eſcape Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let their Pretenſions be what they will.</p>
            <p>Since then God hath repleniſht our Hearts with his Grace, and hath not with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> held his heavenly Manna from us, but daily owns us by his comfortable Preſence, to our great ſatisfaction, under the Omiſſion of theſe things, ſupplying our Wants and Neceſſities as we have recourſe unto him, in that which ever hath acceſs unto him, having our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:172527:33"/>
Dependancy on him, who enables and ſtrengthens thoſe of us <note n="*" place="margin">For we intend not to Apologize for thoſe who tho' they may be call'd by our Name, yet live looſly and walk diſorderly, and are Blemiſhes and a Grief to us; which yet ought to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to their Inſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity or Unwatchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not to the In-ſufficiency of the Prin-ci-ple they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to.</note> that retain our Primitive Sincerity and Integrity, to lead a Sober, Pious, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Life, as becomes the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt, which is the certain Product of Spiritual Grace; and foraſmuch as our Oppoſers acknowledge it to be but an outward viſible Sign, and dare not ſay that the inward Spiritual Grace is tied to it, nor that 'tis of abſolute neceſſity to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; with what Reaſon do they Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian us, and ſo load us with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies and Accuſations on this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, uſing it as an Inſtance to black<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en us, and condemn in groſs our whole Chriſtian Profeſſion, principally from hence, as though 'twere the chief thing that conſtitutes a Chriſtian, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titles him to the Benefits that come by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we think then of perhaps more than two parts in three of their own Aſſembly, who no more practice this than do we, and yet are many of them as ſober People, and if we may
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:172527:34"/>
know (as Chriſt directs us) by their Fruits, are doubtleſs as near the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and no leſs in a State of Grace, than are thoſe who ſo exult in, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue themſelves upon this Performance; which however it may bound and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh particular Societies and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions, 'tis certain no Obſervations nor Performances ſhort of being ruled and governed by the Spirit of Chriſt, as Head, can entitle us to a Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in him; we may make a ſpecious Shew, and carry a Syſtem of Divinity in our Heads, but if he rules not our Hearts we are none of his. 'Twere well they were as thoughtful to fulfil all Righteouſneſs in every reſpect, and as zealouſly careful and concern'd to obſerve and punctually perform all the Commands and Injunctions to which the Chriſtian Religion obligeth them, and to qualify themſelves to be rightful Inheritors of thoſe Bleſſings and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes pronounced by our Saviour, as they tenaciouſly adhere to this, as tho' 'twere indeed the Sum both of Mens Duty and Enjoyments, and that their Salvation turned upon this very Pin; which yet People may perform while their Wills are unſubdued, and Luſts
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:172527:34"/>
unmortified. But we find that Men have been apt enough to be buſily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about Mint, Annis, and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, whilſt they neglect the weightier Matters, to run into, and cry up, and maintain thoſe exteriour parts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that are reconcilable to an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted State.</p>
            <p>If the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity were leſs taken up about Signs and Shadows, and nice and unneceſſary Scrutinies and Diſtinctions wherewith they perplex it, and more devoted to obſerve the weighty, important, and indiſpenſable Precepts of Chriſt, and demonſtrate the Power that Chriſtianity hath over their Minds, by affording ſignal Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their being his true Diſciples, and righful Heirs of his Kingdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in meaſure inveſted with his Divine Vertues and Graces, we ſhould have leſs Envy, Variance, Back-biting, and Detraction, which weakens the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of Piety, and gives our common Enemy an advantage over us; and more Chriſtian Love, Peace, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and good Neighbourhood amongſt us. If all that means well did but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue Vertue, love it, and encourage it where-ever it appears, and hate Vice
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:172527:35"/>
and Evil in all, and diſcountenance it every where, and make theſe the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Chriſtian Charity, rather than Parallel Opinions in leſſer Matters, 'twould bring us nearer together, and more advance True Piety, than all their contending about different Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in things far leſs eſſential. God, who regards not Names, but Natures, knows among all Nations and People who are his; and the Rule he left us to know alſo was their Fruits, their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being the exertion of their Wills; all Mankind are either under the Power and Conduct of the Spirit of God, or elſe of the Devil; all are either Carnal or Spiritual - minded, and as is the ſpring and bent of their Deſires and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, ſo is their Actions; each Birth have their proper Products, which are contrary to each other. So that let what Notions or Opinions ſoever poſſeſs Mens Heads, they live according to that Spirit and Principle that governs their Hearts. We cannot gather Grapes of Thorns, nor Figs of Thiſtles; no Fountain ſends forth bitter Water and ſweet at the ſame time. 'Tis an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> Truth, Thoſe that live in Envy and Strife, and bring forth the Fruits
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:172527:35"/>
of the Fleſh, are of their Father the<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 9.</note> Devil; and thoſe who by the Spirit mortifies thoſe corrupt Luſts and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and bring forth the Fruits of of the Spirit, adorning the Doctrin of God our Saviour, by a ſober, godly, righteous Life, are of God; for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in<note place="margin">1 John 3. 10.</note> the Children of God are manifeſt from the Children of the Devil.</p>
            <p>Thus have we candidly, though briefly, expreſt our real Opinion and Belief in thoſe Points in which we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend our Adverſaries have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd moſt to expoſe us, which we hope may prove ſatisfactory to thoſe who are not reſolved to think ill of us: but to ſpeak fully to every critical, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling Objection, were a tedious Task, as well as vaſtly beyond the Extent of our Deſign. We requeſt our ferious Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to hear and ſee for themſelves, and not take things upon truſt from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to judge the things they know not, but condemn us by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay; don't be impoſed upon by thoſe whoſe peeviſh humours would have all do like themſelves, who either look not at all, or but very coyly into the Books of thoſe they have taken a Pet againſt,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:172527:36"/>
whoſe Perſwaſion in ſome things differs from what they have pronounced Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, as tho' Truth were their pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar incloſure, which yet certainly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues either a great deal of Prejudice, or a feeble and fleeting Judgment, that dares not truſt it ſelf: Were our Books ſtuft with ſuch palpable Errors as is ſuggeſted, ſurely 'twere not ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous reading them: Who fears to read the Alcharon? But on the contrary, 'tis a ſtrong indication that they contain much truth; for as 'tis the proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Underſtanding, ſo where it appears with a clear Evidence, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Peoples own Experience, 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forcible and prevalent upon the Minds of thoſe who diligently ſeek it for love of it, and willingly depoſit all preingagements of Mind in its diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Be then ſo juſt to us, and kind to your ſelves, as to relinquiſh all Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and Prepoſſeſſions, and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially examine the truth of theſe things; ſearch the Sacred Scriptures diligently, with an inclination rather to find and embrace Truth, than to ſupport a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Opinion; try whether 'tis ſo or not, comparing it with your own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences and the Witneſs of God in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:172527:36"/>
your own Hearts. Though our Belief in ſome of theſe Particulars don't ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly quadrate to that of our Oppoſers, it don't therefore neceſſarily follow, 'tis not agreeable to Truth and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; nor can they give us any infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible aſſurance, that their Conceptions are a true Standard of Truth, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they vend their Apprehenſions as the only Orthodox, yes, and are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed too with thoſe that can't be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cermined by them.</p>
            <p>We have no Deſign carrying on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Curtain, howſoever our Sober Demeanour may be uncharitably (not to ſay maliciouſly) inſinuated, as only a Cover of Sheeps Cloating upon the Wolves Nature; and our moſt Solemn Declaration of our Belief in ſeveral Religious Points (being undeniable Truths) conſtrued, and ſuggeſted by ſome Men as only a fair Cover where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we guild over our Poyſon, that it may paſs the leſs ſuſpected, and be the more glibly ſwallowed. What think you, is not this the heighth of Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and Envy in the abſtract? Would they themſelves be content to be thus interpreted? We have no intent to decoy and trapan People, that we ſhould
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:172527:37"/>
walk under a diſguiſe, which Intreagues uſually have intereſt at one end of them, which can't be our caſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who neither give nor take Money for Preaching; ſo that the increaſe of our Numbers will not fill our Coffers. We have no other Intereſt to promote, but the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of True Piety and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: and having Love and Good-will to all People, more eſpecially to thoſe whoſe Minds are awakened, and Hearts warmed, having true ſervent Deſires, and living Breathings towards God, thirſting after a nearer and more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory knowledge of, and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, than barely a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and hear-ſay of him, and therefore what we have found advantageous, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant and ſatisfactory to us, in our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied purſuit after Peace with him, that we recommend to others. We call People home to the Gift of God in themſelves, which only can do them good, that every one may know the good Shepheard and Biſhop of Souls for themſelves, and hear and know his Voice in them, from that of a ſtranger, and learn of him and follow him, who is pure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ever leads to Purity and Holineſs, that ſo his offering up of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:172527:37"/>
for them, may be of benefit to them, and they experience the great Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God; for impreſs this upon your Minds, and take it along with you, That notwithſtanding our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath paid a Ranſom for us, and made an Attonement through the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood of his Croſs; yet if we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience not the end of his Coming, and Death effected, and anſwered in our ſelves, it ſhall avail us nothing; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we know him a Saviour and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter near; except we know a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Divine Light and Life, to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate our Minds, to revive and warm our languiſhing Hearts, to beget and increaſe true Love to God, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith, that gives victory to convert us, and govern our Thoughts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and regulate our Wills<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and limit our Deſires, and bridle our Tongues, to excite holy Inclinations, and keep up a due Heat in our Chriſtianity, and ſtrengthens our Minds in that which is good and well-pleaſing to God: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we know theſe things in and for our ſelves, all our outſide ſhew of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is but vain, and our profeſſion of Chriſt ſhall profit us nothing, but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:172527:38"/>
we ſhall lye down in ſorrow at laſt; for none are Chriſt's, but thoſe that<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 9, 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> have his Spirit, and are influenced by it; nor are any Children of God, but thoſe that are led by the Spirit of God; which begets in the Mind a deteſtation of Sin and Evil, and a love to Purity, Goodneſs and Vertue; wherefore, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide all Strife and Animoſities, all Envying and Evil-ſpeaking, let us ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor that which is Evil, and cleave to<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 9.</note> that which is Good, and addreſs our ſelves with a due and humble Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the accompliſhment of that moſt concerning and important Affair of our Lives, the working out our Salvation. And let every one follow the Lord faithfully, according to what is made known to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> knowing that we ſhall be judged according to our Knowledge, and that 'twill be happy for thoſe whoſe Wills and Performances correſpond with their Underſtandings, in that Day when all muſt ſtand before the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat of Chriſt, and give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Deeds done in the Body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and receive a Sentence thereafter, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Come ye bleſſed,</hi> or, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi> It won't be
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:172527:38"/>
then of what Congregation or Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith, or of what Perſwaſion amongſt the many waſt thou: among all which there will then be but two ſorts, the Sheep and the Goats; thoſe that heard the Shepheard's Voice and followed him, who were guided and governed by the good Spirit of God in their Hearts; and thoſe who wrapping their Talent in a Napkin, ſtifled Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, and neglecting the Day of their Viſitation, continued under the dark Power of the Evil One. One may go a great way, and make a fair ſhew of Religion and Piety<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet be turned to the left hand; 'tis not having our Heads filled with curious ſublime Notions, though of never ſo fine and elevated a Speculation; let's trim and garniſh our Lamps never ſo finely, 'twill not adminiſter an entrance without the Heavenly Oil, without that Holy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Unction fills our Hearts, enlightens our Minds, and inflames our Affections to a due Watchfulneſs and Obedience to its Teachings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are the moſt aſſured Marks of our being really in Chriſt, in whom only our acceptance is.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:172527:39"/>That you with us, and we with you, may ſo circumſpectly live up to Light that and Knowledge given by Chriſt, as that our Conſciences may not condemn us; but that, having finiſhed our Days here with comfort, we may lay down our Heads in Peace, with a well-grounded Hope of a Joyful Reſurrection, and have Boldneſs in the Day of Judgment, is our Hearty Deſire.</p>
            <p>If what we have Written for your Information, may find ſome place with thoſe, who, being impartial, and inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, have room to receive it, and that it Contributes to their Benefit and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, we have our End: But for thoſe who are full, or are critical, and ready to Carpe at every Word or Sentence that is not plac'd to their Mind, if not alſo pre-judge it, as 'tis not intended for them; ſo we don't ſuppoſe 'twill Prove to their good Liking, nor meet with a Reception amongſt them. For we don't propoſe to reconcile our whole Belief and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion in Religious Matters to that of our Oppoſers, who notwithſtanding, what we have writ, we expect will yet
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:172527:39"/>
accuſe us of Error. However, having thus farr declar'd ourſelves in the moſt neceſſary Points of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we don't think ourſelves farther oblidged to anſwer the Cavils and Criticiſms of ſuch who may appear contentious, and will never want ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to object againſt thoſe that comes not up in all things exactly to their Level: whom yet we adviſe, rather to be quiet, and ſtudy to know and govern themſelves, according to that Religion that is pure and undefiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and leads to viſit and aſſiſt the Fatherleſs, and Widows in their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,<note place="margin">Jam. 1. 27.</note> and to keep themſelves from the Spots and Defilements of this World. Were this (as it ought) our Principal Care and Concern in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, we ſhould have little mind or leiſure to differ about Matters of leſs moment: and while we ſeem zealouſly to contend about Religion fruſtrate its end. We ſhould not be taken up in diſputing what that Principle is which God hath plac'd in us to do us good, and in mean time neglect its aſſiſtance, and obſtruct its Operation upon the Mind, but be given up to be leave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:172527:40"/>
and changed by it, that we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> partake of the Bleſſings thereof; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> with it build on the Foundation whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God hath laid, that which may abi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the fiery Tryal. To which we reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend you, and remains your peaceab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and loving Neighbours,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W.C. A.P. J.H., <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
